''One glance from her eyes
would turn them to stone...
＂被她看一眼就能把他们变成石头...
''but all was not yet lost.
＂但一切并未成定数
''Suddenly, the Doctor found a sword
at his feet, picked it up
“突然, 博士在他脚边发现了一把剑, 他拾了起来
''and with one stroke slew the monster.''
＂一举斩杀了那个怪物＂
- A sword!
- That's it! You're meant to use it like Perseus.
- 一把剑！  - 这就对了，你得像 Perseus 那样用它
(Perseus: 珀尔修斯, 宙斯之子, 砍下了美杜莎的头)
- Maybe it's another trap.
- Doctor, please!
- 这可能又是一个陷阱  - 博士, 快啊
No. How can I kill something
that doesn't exist?
不．我怎么能杀死并不存在的东西？
- I've got to open my eyes. I've got to see!
- Wait!
- 我必须睁开我的眼睛, 我要看看  - 等一下！
Perseus. Of course. A mirror.
Perseus. 当然了, 一面镜子
There. Look at her reflection in the mirror. Look!
来, 在镜子里看看她的样子．看！
- Can you see her?  - Yes.
- 你能看到她吗？  - 能
This is how Perseus escaped.
He looked at her reflection in his polished shield.
Perseus 就是这么逃脱的, 他是通过他闪亮的盔甲去看美杜莎的
There's no danger in the reflection.
通过反射去看没有危险
''Cancel. Cancel. Cancel.
＂取消, 取消, 取消
''The Doctor test report failure.''
"对博士的测试宣告失败＂
Failure?
失败?
(BEEPING)
(ROBOTIC VOICE) Attention. Attention.
There is a stranger inside the building.
注意, 注意, 楼里面现在有一个陌生人
Call out the search party.
呼叫搜索队
- Ah, the young traveller. I had wondered as much.
- Have you been sent to find me?
- 啊，年轻的旅客, 我还好奇呢  - 你是被派来找我的？
His companions were in a state of anxiety
about his whereabouts.
他的同伴对于他在哪里感到很焦虑
Companions! Zoe and the Doctor!
Where are they?
同伴！Zoe 和博士！ 他们在哪儿？
- Safe.  - You've actually spoken to them?
- 安全着呢  - 你真同他们说过话？
The gentleman desired to know
where I came from and whither I was bound.
那位绅士想知道我从哪里来, 要到哪里去
- (BUZZING)
- What's that?
那是什么？
- I heard nothing.
- Probably that search party.
- 我没听见什么  - 可能是搜索队
By the laws of this Kingdom,
every chamber must be searched.
根据这个王国的法律, 每个房间都要搜索
- If they find me, I'm done for.
- You should be put to death.
- 如果他们找到我, 我就完了  - 你必会被处死
- What about you?
- I shall come to no harm.
- 你怎么样？  - 我不会受到任何伤害
If you give me away this time, I'm finished.
如果这次你把我供出去, 我完蛋了
I was ready with the hazard of my life
to defend his person.
我准备冒着我生命的危险来保护他的人
(BUZZING AND BEEPING)
Where have they gone? The white robots.
他们去哪儿了？那些白色机器人
Young sir, I do assure you,
there were no such persons here.
年轻的先生, 我向你保证, 这里没有这样的人
Aye. Robots or not,
I'm getting out of this place.
是, 不管是不是机器人, 我要离开这个地方
You desire your liberty?
你想要自由？
Yes. I got in all right, but how do I get out?
是的．我顺利地进来了, 但我怎么出去？
After some consideration,
I was of the opinion that...
经过一番考虑, 我的看法是...
Go on, go on.
继续, 继续
..this was altogether impossible.
..所有这些都是不可能的
Oh, yes. That's the citadel, all right.
The question is, how do we get up there?
噢, 是了, 那就是城堡, 好吧．问题是, 我们怎么上去？
- It's a long way to climb.  - Zoe, duck!
- 要爬上去太远了  - Zoe, 蹲下!
- The Karkus!  - You are my prisoners!
- 是 Karkus!  - 你们是我的俘虏了！
- It's the Karkus.  - What?
- 是 Karkus  - 什么？
You will come out
and put ze hands above ze head.
你们得出来, 把手举到头上
- You know. He's fictional too.
- Obey or I fire.
- 知道吗, 他也是虚构的  - 不照做我就开枪了
- That thing...what sort of a gun is that?
- (ZOE) An anti-molecular ray disintegrator.
- 那个东西...是一把什么枪?  - 反分子射线分解枪
Rubbish! Such a weapon
is scientifically impossible. It doesn't exist.
胡说！这样的武器在科学上是不可能的, 它并不存在
Hargh!
哈！
- That takes care of that, doesn't it?
- I shall tear you limb from limb!
- 这就搞定了那个，是吧？   - 我要把你们撕成碎片
Doctor, be careful. He could do it, you know.
The Karkus has superhuman strength.
博士, 小心, 他能做到的。Karkus 有这超人的力量
You will be mincemeat!
你会成为碎片！
Quickly, Doctor, say it!
You know he's a fictional character.
快点，博士, 说啊！你知道他是个虚构人物
But I've never heard of him!
但我从来没有听说过他！
(这个 Karkus 并不是一个已知故事中的人物, 所以博士并不认识)
- Hargh!  - What are you doing?
- 哈！  - 你在做什么？
Please, I'm sure we can talk this over.
拜托, 我确定我们可以谈判解决
- Zoe!  - Lesson 17!
- Zoe!  - 第17招
- Be careful.  - Oh, dear!
- 小心   - 哦, 天啊!
(ZOE) Lesson 32!
第32招
Don't do anything rash!
别莽撞！
- Mercy!  - You'd better submit.
- 饶命！  - 你最好投降
- The neck can't take much pressure.
- Help!
- 脖子可承受不了多少压力  - 救命！
- Do you submit?  - I submit!
- 你投降吗？  - 我投降!
That's better.
这好多了
I am your slave. Command me.
我是你的奴隶, 给我命令吧
- Do you know the way to the citadel?
- I know it.
- 你知道去城堡的路吗？  - 我知道
Take us up there, there's a good chap.
带我们去吧, 那里有一个好小伙
- (CLICKS)  - I obey.
我服从
Well, thank you, Mr...
What did you say his name was?
好, 谢谢你...你说他叫什么名字来着？
- K-A-R-K-U-S.
- Oh, yes. Mr Karkus. Thank you.
- K-A-R-K-U-S.  - 哦, 是的, Karkus 先生, 谢谢你
We won't be needing you any longer. Run along.
我们不再需要你了, 你走吧
I obey.
我服从
- Come along.  - You can't just ring the bell.
- 快过来  - 你可不能按门铃
Why not? It's the usual way.
为什么不？一般都这样啊
(JANGLING BELL)
Are you sure this is a good idea?
你确定这是个好主意吗？
State your name and attribution.
报上名号和来历
I am the Karkus.
我是 Karkus
- And your attribution?
- What's that?
- 你的来历呢？  - 那是什么？
Shh! Year 2000 comic strip creation.
The ''Hourly Telepress''.
嘘！2000年漫画作品 《每时电讯》
Authenticated. You may enter.
验证通过, 你可以进来
(CREAKING)
Come on. You heard them giving orders to look for me.
Why do you suppose that happened?
好啦，你听到他们下令搜寻我了．你觉得为什么会发生这事？
I conjecture these were orders
given by some person in authority.
我猜想这些是某个当权者下达的命令
- The Master?  - It is possible.
- 大师？  - 有可能
Now I'm getting somewhere.
现在我有点明白了
Listen. If there aren't any robots,
who do you think was carrying out those orders?
听着，如果没有那些机器人，你觉得会是谁来执行那些命令？
I mean, who was I hiding from?
我是说，我是在躲谁呢？
- Why, sir, the Yahoos.
- Who's the Yahoos?
- 是那些 Yahoo  - Yahoo 是谁？
A cursed race of inferior creatures.
I never beheld so disagreeable an animal.
一个被诅咒的低等生物种族。我从来没有见过这么令人不愉快的动物
I haven't seen any Yahoos,
you haven't seen any robots!
我从未见过一个 Yahoo，而你从未见过一个机器人！
- Jamie!  - Stay where you are!
- Jamie!  - 待在原地别动！
There's an electrical gadget
around here somewhere that sets off an alarm gong.
这里某处有一个电子设备会触发警报
I walked through it, the gong went off
and they sent robots after me.
我从下面走过，警铃就响了，他们就派机器人来追我
- Robots? You mean the same ones we saw before?
- Big white ones.
- 机器人? 我们之前看见的那些？  - 白色大个的
- Doctor, did you hear that?
- Yes. I thought they'd turn up.
- 博士, 你听到了吗？  - 是的, 我想他们会出现的
It's a simple photo-electric cell.
I'd better lift you over it.
只是一个简单的光电元件。我可以抬你过去
- Careful, because...
- Oh, my jacket.
- 小心, 因为...   - 噢, 我的夹克
What happened when you left the tunnel?
你离开隧道后发生了什么？
I was chased by one of those tin soldiers.
Lucky I climbed up the cliff up here.
我被一个锡兵追赶, 幸运的是我爬上了这个绝壁
- The thing is, how do we get out?
- I'm not leaving yet. I'm here on business.
- 问题是，我们怎么出去？  - 我暂时还不走，我来这里有事
The Doctor's made up his mind
He is going to see the Master.
博士已经下定决心了，他打算去见大师
This resolution perhaps may appear
bold and dangerous.
这个决定似乎是比较大胆而且危险
- There you are, you see?
- Why do you say that?
- 对吧，你看？  - 你为什么这么说？
I think you should not be here.
我觉得你不应该在这里
The Master makes rules for his kingdom.
It is unwise for you to disobey.
大师为他的王国制定规则．你不服从是不明智的
So you think we shouldn't see the Master?
所以你觉得我们不应该去见大师？
If you'll follow my advice,
swear a peace with the Master and his kingdom.
如果你们听我的建议，与大师和这个王国和平共处
Find yourself a place to lodge, stay quietly
with the expectation that things would mend.
自己找一个地方安顿下来, 安静地等着事情好转
Yes. Well, I'll see.
I'll think it over very carefully.
是的．好, 我再看看, 我要仔细考虑一下
- Your servant.  - Your servant.
- 为你服务  - 为你服务
Your servant.
为你服务
- You're not going to do as he says?
- No. Of course not. I said I'd think it over.
- 你不打算按他说的做吧？  - 不，当然不。我说过我会考虑
I've thought it over. We're staying on and fighting on.
我现在已经考虑过了．我们会留下来继续斗争
But we'll be fighting in the dark. We won't know
where the next attack will come from.
但我们是在两眼一抹黑地斗争，都不知道下一次攻击会从哪里来
- Medusa was bad enough.
- Ah, Medusa. Yes, I read about that on this machine here.
- 美杜莎就够糟的了  - 啊, 美杜莎．是的，我在这个机器上读到过这个
- Wee words keep coming out of it all the time
- Let's have a look.
- 一直有单词挨个地从那里面出来  - 我们看看
There. Look.
那里, 看
''Cancel. Doctor test report failure.''
"取消．对博士的测试宣告失败＂
- I think I'm beginning to understand.
- I wish I was.
- 我想我开始明白了  - 真期望我也能
When somebody writes about an incident
after it's happened, that is history.
一个事件发生之后如果有人写了它, 这就成了历史
- Hm?   - Yes.
- 嗯？  - 是的
But when the writing comes first,
that's fiction.
但如果写在了前面, 那就是虚构故事
If we'd have fallen into the Master's trap,
we would have become fiction.
如果我们落入了大师的圈套, 我们就会变成虚构故事
That's horrible. Come on. Let's get out of here before too late.
这太可怕了, 快点，我们离开这里，不然来不及了
Zoe, don't go... No! Don't go through there.
Zoe，不要走...不！不要走那里
(BEEPING)
Attention.
There are still strangers at large.
注意, 仍然有陌生人在逃
Renew the search.
The strangers must be found.
重启搜索．必须要找到这些陌生人
- What are we going to do?
- I mean that's funny. Gulliver walked through there.
- 我们要做什么？  - 这很奇怪，格列弗就从那里过去的
- Gulliver is not real. We are.
- They're coming! Where can we hide?
- 格列弗不是真实的，我们是  - 他们来了！我们能躲在哪儿？
- No need to hide.
- Why not? If they find us...
- 没必要躲起来  - 为什么不？如果他们找到我们...
- Let them find us.
- You mean just stand here and wait?
- 让他们来找  - 你是说就站在这里等着？
Yes. Why not? We'll ask for
an interview with the Master.
是的, 为什么不？我们会要求跟大师会面
- They may not give us time to ask...
- Look!
- 他们可能不给我们时间来提要求...  - 看！
- (BUZZING AND BEEPING)
- Are you looking for us, by any chance?
你们是在找我们吗，有可能吗？
We... We demand an interview
with the Master!
我们...我们要求跟大师见面！
(MAN) Ho, ho!
How very fortunate. Do come in, Doctor.
呵, 呵！非常幸运啊, 进来吧, 博士
I've been expecting you.
我一直在等你
Oh, don't be alarmed.
Won't you walk into my parlour?
噢, 不要惊慌．你不打算走进我的客厅吗？
Said the spider to the fly.
说得蜘蛛都会飞了
Come along.
过来吧
(LOW HUMMING)
- It's hard to see anything.
- Where are you?
- 什么都很难看清  - 你在哪儿？
Here! Patiently waiting.
这里！耐心地等待着
Oh! Oh, Doctor. This is a great pleasure.
噢！噢, 博士, 真是不胜之喜啊
And your two young companions.
Now let me see...
还有你的两位年轻同伴．现在让我看看...
Oh, yes, yes. Zoe and Jamie.
I have your dossiers here in front of me.
噢, 是的是的，Zoe 和 Jamie, 我面前这里有你们的档案
- You appear to be well organised.
- Yes. Indeed. We have to be.
- 看起来你还组织得挺好  - 是的, 的确。我们必须的
Running this place
requires enormous attention to detail.
运作这个地方需要大量对细节的关注
- It's a responsible position, but very rewarding.
- Responsible, eh?
- 这是一个责任重大的位置, 但回报很不错  - 责任重大, 嗯？
- To someone else?
- Not to someone. Another power.
- 对其他人的责任吗？  - 不是对其他人．是对另一种力量
Higher than any you could begin to imagine.
高过你们任何人所能想象
Oh, I must congratulate you
on the great skill
噢, 我必须得恭喜你, 你有着非凡的技巧
in which you tackled
in various stages of your examination.
在不同阶段的测试中展现出来的那些技巧
What is the purpose of all these tests?
这些测试的目的是什么？
You know, when I was first brought here myself,
I was as bewildered as you are.
你要知道，我当初被带到这里来的时候, 我跟你一样不知所措
- How long have you been here?
- I left England in the summer of 1926.
- 你在这里多久了？  - 我是1926年夏天离开英格兰的
It was a very hot day, I remember.
那天热别热, 我记得
I think I must have dozed off over my desk,
and when I awoke...
我想我肯定是在桌子上睡着了, 等我醒来...
But that's a long story.
但这是一个很长的故事了
Did you ever hear of the adventures
of Captain Jack Harkaway?
你听说过Jack Harkaway船长的历险吗？
No, I can't say that I... Wait a minute.
没, 我得说我没有...等一下
- A serial in a boys' magazine?
- The ''Ensign''.
- 在一本小男孩杂志上连载的？  - 《少尉》
And for 25 years,
I delivered 5,000 words every week.
整整25年, 我每周交付5000个词
You're a writer.
你是个作家
25 years, 5,000 words a week?
25 年, 每周 5000 单词？
- That's over half a million words.
- Yes. It was probably a record.
- 那可超过半个百万了  - 是的, 这可能是一项记录
That's why I was selected to work here.
这就是为什么我被选中在这里工作
- You're the one that is in charge of all this?
- In one sense, yes.
- 你就是那个掌控所有这些的人？  - 某种程度上, 是的
Yes. Or is all this in charge of you?
哦, 或者是所有这些掌控了你？
My brain is the source of the creative power
which keeps this whole operation going.
我的大脑是创造力的源泉, 而创造力保持这里的全力运转
I see. That means
that you are virtually a prisoner.
我明白了．这就是说你其实也是一个囚徒
No, no.
不, 不是
(HUMMING)
You... You must excuse me for one moment.
你...你必须原谅我失配一会儿
- Let's get out of here.
- Yes. It gives me the creeps.
- 我们离开这里吧  - 是的，都让我起鸡皮疙瘩了
- No. I need to find out more.
- You keep him talking. Zoe and me will find another way out.
- 不, 我需要查明更多情况  -你跟他一直说话，Zoe 和我另外找一条路出去
No, Jamie. I think we'd be safer
if we all stick together.
不，Jamie. 我觉得我们团结在一起的话更安全点
- (HUMMING STOPS)
- Sorry to have kept you waiting. Where were we?
- 抱歉让你们久等了．刚才说到哪儿了？
You were about to answer my question.
Are you a prisoner here?
你这要回答我的问题, 你是这里的囚徒吗？
No. No, I wouldn't say that.
不, 不, 我不会这么说
In fact, I rather like being here.
I have everything I could possibly want.
事实上, 我挺喜欢待在这里．我想要的基本都有了
This vast library
with all the known works of fiction.
这个巨大的宝库, 收藏了所有已知的虚构故事
All the masterpieces written by Earthmen
since the beginning of time.
自从有史以来，所有地球人撰写的杰作
- I don't think he noticed.
- No. Let's try down there.
- 我觉得他没注意到  - 不, 我们试试那边
I see, yes. And only an Earthman-type creature
has the power to create fiction.
我明白了, 是的．而且只有地球人才有创造虚构故事的能力
- The power to imagine.
- Exactly.
- 想象力  - 正是
This is one field in which
the intelligence I serve cannot compete.
这个领域正是我所服务的智慧生命所不能匹敌的
They need a man of boundless imagination
as a...um...
他们需要一个具有无边想象力的人, 作为....
a powerhouse, a lifeline.
作为他们的发电厂, 生命线
What is this intelligence you serve
and why was I brought here?
你服务的这种智慧生命是什么？为什么我被带到这里来？
Well, as you see, I'm no longer young,
哦, 如你所见, 我已经不再年轻了
whereas you, Doctor, are ageless.
而你, 博士, 是不老的
You exist outside
the barriers of time and space.
你存在于时间与空间的屏障之外
And you want me...
所以你想要我...
To take over this unique situation.
To take my place.
接管这个独特的地方, 接替我的位置
- I refuse!  - (HUMMING)
我拒绝！
(FLAT VOICE) Refusal is impossible.
拒绝是不可能的
You are here to serve us.
There is no alternative.
你到这里服侍我们, 没有别的选择
- We've got to find a way out here.
- There must be a door somewhere.
- 我们必须找到一条出路  - 肯定某个地方有道门
- Look, if we can get the Doctor away...
- Jamie!
- 如果我们能把博士弄走...  - Jamie!
No. Back this way!
不, 回这边来！
Resistance is useless.
抵抗是无用的！
Submit your will for the sake
of the greater good. It has been decided.
为了更大的利益, 投降吧．这已经决定了
I refuse.
I shall make that decision for myself.
我拒绝．我将自己为自己做出决定
- (HUMMING STOPS)
- You will find there is only one decision open to you.
你会发现，只有一个决定对你是开放的
(HUMMING)
Mission accomplished.
Procedure as arranged.
任务完成．按计划过程处理
- What does that mean?
- The latest chapter of the serial story.
- 那是什么意思？  - 连载故事的最后一章
I'll read you the last sentence.
我给你读读最后的一句
''Zoe and Jamie attempted to escape,
"Zoe 和 Jamie 试图逃走
''but in making through the library,
"但在试图通过图书馆的途中
''they were ambushed by a party of guards
and overpowered.''
"他们被一队警卫伏击, 被打败了＂
Oh, no! Jamie! Zoe!
噢, 不！Jamie! Zoe!
Are you prepared to co-operate now?
你现在准备好合作了吗？
Your life in return for theirs?
Is that a bargain?
用你的命换他们的命？这样不值吗？
(CHUCKLES)
Look.
看！
(BUZZING)
(THEY GROAN)
- Oh, Jamie, my eyes!
- I can't see. Where are you?
- 哦, Jamie, 我的眼睛!  - 我看不见了, 你在哪儿？
Quick, back. Get away.
快, 回去, 赶紧走
Zoe, here, quick.
Zoe, 这边, 快
No. It's a book! Back out again.
不, 这是本书！再退出去
- Oh! Oh, push!
- Open up! It's closing!
- 噢！噢, 推！  - 打开！它要关上了
- No!  - Aagh!
- 不!  - 啊！